Guide to the Robert B. Fisher Photograph Collection and Papers WA MSS S-2823
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Robert B. Fisher photograph collection and papers
1840-1998
WA MSS S-2823
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
24.2
(35 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
This collection chiefly consists of photographs collected by Robert B. Fisher, but also includes his subject files and a small quantity of writings related to the history of photography, 1840-1998.
Fisher, Robert B., 1919-2004
Anthony, Edward
Babbitt, Platt D., -1879
Bierstadt Brothers
Keystone View Company
Langenheim Brothers
London Stereoscopic Company
New York Stereoscopic Company
Underwood & Underwood
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Peter E. Palmquist, 2003.
Custodial History
The Robert B. Fisher Photograph Collection and Papers were acquired by Peter E. Palmquist from Fisher, probably in 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile Materials in Box 34 (computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Associated Materials
Robert B. Fisher Collection of Views of Europe (94.R.30). The Getty Research Institute.
Dr. Robert B. Fisher Collection. Museum of Local History, Fremont, California.
Robert B. Fisher (1919-2004)
In 1950, Robert Burns Fisher moved to Washington Township, California, and established a medical practice in San Jose. Fisher was keenly interested in local history, especially pioneer families who settled the area. He researched and sought the preservation of historic resources in Southern Alameda County. In 1962, he founded Mission Peak Heritage Foundation in Fremont, California. Fisher was an expert on European photography and a collector photographs, as well as a contributor of articles on the history of photography to the Journal of the West and Daguerreian Annual.
Scope and Contents
This collection chiefly consists of photographs collected by Robert B. Fisher, but also includes his subject files and a small quantity of writings related to the history of photography, 1840-1998.
Photographs in the collection include cased photographs, stereographs, glass transparencies, and lantern slides. The collection includes a particularly rich variety of stereograph formats, including daguerreotype stereographs, ambrotype stereographs, tintype stereographs, glass stereographs, salted paper print stereographs, tissue stereographs, and card stereographs. The collection also provides visual documentation of the Niagara Falls region and the Great Britain during the middle of the nineteenth century. Photographers and stereograph publishers with significant quantities of photographic material in the collection include Edward Anthony, Platt Delascus Babbitt, Bierstadt Brothers, Keystone View Company, Langenheim Brothers, London Stereoscopic Company, New York Stereoscopic Company, and Underwood & Underwood.
Printed material in the collection includes illustrated articles, tear sheets, and prints with illustrations primarily published during the nineteenth century that Fisher compiled principally as resources for identifying photographic images.
Papers in the collection relate mainly to Fisher's photographic collection and the history of photography, as well as drafts of his articles in the Journal of the West and Daguerreian Annual.
Arrangement
Organized into six series: I. Cased Photographs, 1840-circa 1860. II. Stereographs, 1850-1975. III. Glass Transparencies and Lantern Slides, circa 1850-circa 1921. IV. Copy Photographs, circa 1980-circa 1997. V. Printed Material, 1842-1932. VI. Papers, 1977-1998.
Daguerreian Annual; Journal of the West; Photographers; Photographic industry; Photography; Photography -- History; Photography, Stereoscopic; Great Britain -- Pictorial works; New York (State) -- Pictorial works; Niagara Falls (N.Y. and Ont.) -- Pictorial works; Ontario -- Pictorial works; Ambrotypes (photographs); Black-and-white transparencies; Cased photographs; Daguerreotypes (photographs); Lantern slides; Photographic prints; Salted paper prints; Stereographs; Tintypes (prints); Tissue stereographs; Anthony, Edward; Babbitt, Platt D., -1879; Fisher, Robert B., 1919-2004; Bierstadt Brothers; Keystone View Company; Langenheim Brothers; London Stereoscopic Company; New York Stereoscopic Company; Underwood & Underwood; Palmquist, Peter E. -- Ownership
- Cased Photographs, 1840-circa 1860; Series I; 5.2; 6 boxes
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into four subseries: Daguerreotypes, Ambrotypes, Tintype, and Cases.
  The contents of each subseries are arranged alphabetically under headings for identified creators, followed by items with unidentified creators
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of cased photographs, which are usually daguerreotypes, ambrotypes, or tintypes mounted in sturdy, boxlike cases. It includes thirty-nine daguerreotypes, two ambrotypes, and one tintype, as well as seven examples of empty cases.
  - Daguerreotypes
    - Anthony, Clark Co.
      Biographical/Historical note
      Edward Anthony (1819-1888) and James R. Clark (died 1848), also known as Isaiah or Isaac Clark, were partners in the firm Anthony, Clark & Co. at 247 Broadway, New York City, 1846-1847
      - Daguerreotype, not in a case, studio portrait of a woman, 1846-1847 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Sixth-plate daguerreotype
        Label affixed to the verso of the image package: "Manufactured expressly for Anthony, Clark, & Co. and warranted perfect"
        Pencil inscription on image package tape: "Resealed 3-5-91 KA"
    - Beard, Richard, Jabez Hogg, or Arthur Schomberg Kerr
      General note
      See Robert B. Fisher, "The Beard Photographic Franchise in England," The Daguerreian Annual (1992): 73-95
      Richard Beard (1801-1885) was an English entrepreneur active in photography from 1840 to 1861
      - Daguerreotype, in a half case, studio portrait of a man seated, circa 1843 (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Ninth-plate hand-tinted daguerreotype
        Brass gilt Wharton pinchbeck oval mat
        Inscription on verso of plate: "J. H. No. 2." Inscription may refer to Jabez Hogg
      - Daguerreotype, in a plate holder, studio portrait of a man, circa 1843 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Brass gilt Wharton pinchbeck oval mat and plate holder
        Inscription on verso of plate: "Kerr 2." Inscription may refer to Arthur Schomberg Kerr (1820-1856)
    - Beckers Piard
      Beckers & Piard was a gallery operated by Alexander Beckers and Victor Picard at 264 Broadway, New York City, 1853-1856
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of a man seated, 1853-1856 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        Custodial History
        Formerly owned by Albert Raborn Phillips (1883-1975)
        Mat hallmarks: "Becker & Picard" and "264 Broadway"
        Ink inscription on hinge: "26"
        Book plate under image package: "Photography, 1839-1889, From the Collection of Albert Raborn Phillips, Jr. c. 1938"
    - Darling, Thomas H.
      Thomas H. Darling operated Darling's Studio in Boston, Massachusetts, 1841-1842
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of a woman seated, 1841-1842 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        Quarter-plate daguerreotype
        Brass mat with a blindstamp: "Darling's Studio" and "Milk St, Boston"
    - Hossauer, Johann George, attributed
      Johann George Hossauer (1794-1874) was a court goldsmith, entrepreneur and inventor in Berlin, Germany.
      - Daguerreotype, not in a case, studio portrait of a man seated, circa 1840-1845 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        Hallmarks on recto of plate: "Hossauer Berlin" and "40"
    - Hogg, Jabez H., attributed
      Jabez H. Hogg (1817-1899)
      - Daguerreotype, in a frame, studio portrait of a woman seated, 1841 August 24 (Box 2)
        Image package holder verso imprinted: "F. Wharton, No. 791, 24 August 1841"
        Pencil inscription on image package verso: "My Mother"
        See Robert B. Fisher, "The Hogg Connection," The Daguerreian Annual (1990): 101-114
    - Meade Brothers
      The Meade Brothers was a partnership between Henry William Matthew Meade (1823-1865) and Charles Richard Meade (1826-1858). They operated studios under the name throughout in New York State, including Albany, 1845-1850; Buffalo, 1845-1847, and in New York City, 1850-1860.
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of a woman seated, circa 1845-1850 (Box 1, Folder 7)
        Case imprinted on the recto: "Meade Brothers, Exchange, Albany, N.Y."
        Image package includes red wax on verso
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of a man seated and wearing a hat, holding a cane, and leaning on a stack of books, circa 1850 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Case imprinted on the recto: "Meade, Brothers. No. 233, Broadway, N-Y. Opposite Park Fountain"
    - Plumbe, John, 1809-1857
      Plumbe operated franchise studios in Boston, Massachusetts; Philadelphia, Pennsylvania; Salem, Massachusetts; Exeter, New Hampshire; Dubuque, Iowa; New York, New York; Albany, New York; Saratoga Springs, New York; Baltimore, Maryland; New Orleans, Louisiana; and Washington, and District of Columbia
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of a man, identified as H. W. Jennings, circa 1841-1842 (Box 1, Folder 9)
        H. W. Jennings was possibly an attorney in the eastern United States
        Full leather case with a Grecian Urn motif
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of a man, circa 1845 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        Case has a paper lining under the image package printed: "Manufactured at the Plumbe National Daguerrian Depot, New York."
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of a man, circa 1842 (Box 1, Folder 11)
        Case has a green silk pad with a geometric pattern
        Brass mat with an acorn motif
        Pencil inscriptions on tape of image package: "Very early heavy Scovill plate & cut down on right side. 3 corners clipped & sides are flat. 3 initials are written [in the] copper & 'esq'; c. 1842. Retaped 9/8/96 by D.A.W. in Exeter, N. H."
        Conservation work completed by Dennis A. Waters of Exeter, New Hampshire, September 8, 1996
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of a man, circa 1843 (Box 1, Folder 12)
        Sixth-plate daguerreotype with gold toning
        Case has a green silk pad
        Brass mat with an acorn motif with blindstamp: "Plumbe's Patent, October 22, 1842"
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of a man, circa 1845 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Root, Samuel
      From 1851 to 1853, Samuel Root (1819-1889) and Marcus Aurelius Root (1808-1888) were listed as daguerreans at 363 Broadway, New York City. By December 1851, Marcus Root sold his interest in the gallery.
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of a woman, 1852-1853 (Box 3, Folder 14)
        Ninth-plate daguerreotype with gold toning
        Brass mat with an acorn motif with blindstamps: "Patent" and "S. Root, 363 Broadway, N-Y"
    - Shew, William J., attributed
      William J. Shew (1820-1903) was a daguerreotype case maker and photographer in Boston, Massachusetts, and San Francisco, California
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of a woman seated and writing in a book on a table, circa 1844-1849 (Box 3, Folder 15)
        Brass mat with an arched top
        Paper liner under image package printed: "Wm. Shew, miniature case maker, and dealer in plates, lockets, chemicals, and German & American cameras, corner of Court and Howard Sts., Boston."
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of a man, circa 1849 (Box 3, Folder 16)
        Sixth-plate daguerreotype with red wax on its verso
        Brass mat
        Paper liner under image package printed: "Wm. Shew, miniature case maker, and dealer in daguerreotype materials, 123 Washington Street, Boston."
    - Southworth Hawes, attributed
      Southworth & Hawes was a photographic firm operated in Boston, 1843-1863, by Albert Sands Southworth (1811–1894) and Josiah Johnson Hawes (1808–1901)
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of a woman seated and in profile left arm resting on a book on a pillow, circa 1849 (Box 3, Folder 17)
        Swan case with a red pad
    - White, Asa
      Asa White operated daguerrian studios in Boston, Massachusetts, 1843-1850; from 1843-1848, White worked at 20 Washington Street.
      - Daguerreotype, not in a case, studio portrait of a man, 1843-1848 (Box 3, Folder 18)
        Brass oval mat with a label affixed to its recto: "Asa White, 20 Washington St., Boston"
    - Unidentified Photographers
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of a woman, identified as Charlotte Haven Ladd Coues, circa 1840-1842 (Box 3, Folder 19)
        Charlotte Haven Ladd Coues (1813-1900) was a poet in Portsmouth, New Hampshire, as well as the wife of Samuel Elliott Coues (1797-1867), a merchant and civic leader in Portsmouth
        Sixth-plate daguerreotype with a sixteenth plate exposure; plate has red wax on verso
        Brass oval mat
        Paper mat over image package with inscription: "Mrs. C. H. L. Coues, aged about 27, taken about 1840"
        Flip-top case with brown velvet pad.
        Lining paper under image package printed: "A. T. Serrell, fancy case maker, 28 & 30 Cherry-St. New York. Daguerreotype apparatus made to order." Alexander T. Serrell was a dealer and manufacturer of cases in New York City; From 1840 to 1842 he was listed at the rear of 28 Cherry Street.
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of a woman seated and holding a book, 1840-1845 (Box 3, Folder 20)
        Ninth-plate daguerreotype
        Accompanied by a clipped calling card for Julia M. Frost with a manuscript inscription: "Sherman Bronson Warner was engaged to this girl, but she died before they could be married."
        Julia M. Frost is probably Julia Maria Frost (born circa 1824). She married William H. Kirk (born 1818) in Waterbury, Connecticut, in 1845
        Sherman Bronson Warner (1813-1890) was born in Waterbury, Connecticut. He married Lydia Ann Hall (1822-1905) in 1846
      - Daguerreotype, in a half case, studio portrait of a man, 1840-1845 (Box 3, Folder 21)
        Gilt paper mat
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of a man, 1840-1845 (Box 3, Folder 22)
        Sixth-plate daguerreotype; hallmark: "Scovills"
      - Daguerreotype, not in a case, studio portrait of a man, circa 1840-1850 (Box 3, Folder 23)
        Brass octagonal mat
        Brass preserver likely added later
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of a man, 1840-1845 (Box 3, Folder 24)
        Sixth-plate gold-toned daguerreotype
        Flip top plain case
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of a man seated with his arm on a table, 1840-1845 (Box 3, Folder 25)
        Sixth-plate hand-cut daguerreotype
        Plain case with red silk pad
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of two women seated, circa 1843-1850 (Box 4, Folder 26)
        Sixth-plate hand-tinted daguerreotype; hallmark: "Scovills"
        Case manufactured by Mathew B. Brady; imprinted on recto: "M. Brady" and "Case Maker, N.Y."
        Case with a maroon pad
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of a man holding a cane and seated, identified as H. Pierce, circa 1845-1850 (Box 4, Folder 27)
        Sixth-plate gold-toned daguerreotype, hallmark "C" on verso of plate
        Flip-top plain case with brown velvet pad
        Pencil inscription on lining paper behind image package: "Old H. Pierce"
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of a woman seated and holding a book, circa 1845-1850 (Box 4, Folder 28)
        Cardboard mat with a brass border
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of a man with a beard and no moustache, circa 1845-1850 (Box 4, Folder 29)
        Sixteenth-plate daguerreotype
        Case with green velvet pad
      - Daguerreotype, in a half case, studio portrait of a man wearing gloves and seated next to a table with an upturned hat, circa 1845-1850 (Box 4, Folder 30)
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of a boy wearing a plaid dress and seated with his left arm on a table, circa 1845-1850 (Box 4, Folder 31)
        Sixth-plate hand-tinted daguerreotype
        Brass mat and preserver
        Case with a red pad
      - Daguerreotype, not in a case, studio portrait of a man, circa 1845-1850 (Box 4, Folder 32)
        Modern cardboard mat between modern glass and on board
        Inscription on tape: "Matted and reglassed, March 1997, by C. Wahren, New Haven, CT"
        Conservation work completed by Christopher Wahren Fine Photographs in New Haven, Connecticut, March 1997
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of a man seated with his left arm on a table, identified as R. C. Scanland, 1847 July 16 (Box 4, Folder 33)
        Portrait may depict Robert Caldwell Scanland (1825-1895). Scanland was born in Carroll County, Kentucky, died in Pittsfield, Illinois. He served as a captain with the Military Transport Division of the Union army during the American Civil War, and was a friend of Abraham Lincoln
        Plate hallmark in the lower left corner: 40
        Brass arched mat
        Inscription on lining paper behind image package: "R. C. Scanland, July 16, 1847, Cincinnati, Oh."
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of a man, circa 1850 (Box 4, Folder 34)
        Sixteenth-plate hand-tinted daguerreotype
      - Daguerreotype, in a case, studio portrait of a man, circa 1850 (Box 4, Folder 35)
        Quarter-plate hand-tinted daguerreotype
      - Daguerreotype, in a wooden frame, studio portrait of a man, identified as Reuben Markham Stackpole, circa 1850 (Box 5)
        Newspaper clipping on the verso of the frame documents the death of Reuben Markham Stackpole (1792-1883) in Boston, Massachusetts, April 1, 1883
      - Two daguerreotypes, in a case, one daguerreotype is studio portrait a woman, and the other daguerreotype is a studio portrait of a man, circa 1850-1855 (Box 4, Folder 36)
        Both sixteenth-plate hand-tinted daguerreotypes
  - Ambrotypes
    - Copy ambrotype, in a case, studio portrait of a man posed sitting and wearing a hat, circa 1855 (Box 6, Folder 37)
      Sixth-plate clear glass ambrotype
    - Ambrotype, in a case, studio portrait of a boy posed sitting with his arm resting on a book and table, circa 1860 (Box 6, Folder 38)
      Half-plate clear glass ambrotype
      Thermoplastic case manufactured by S. Peck & Company, circa 1858. It has a Washington Monument decoration. Missing pad
      Lining paper under image package: "Genuine union case improved S. Peck's patent, Oct. 3d 1854, H Halverson's patent Aug. 7th 1855, assigned to S. Peck, S. Peck's patent, Feb. 5, 1856"
  - Tintype
    - Tintype, in a half case, studio portrait of a girl, circa 1860 (Box 6, Folder 39)
      Ninth-plate hand-tinted tintype
  - Cases
    - Sage, William, circa 1842
      William Sage (born 1818) was a daguerrean case maker and merchant in Berlin, Connecticut
      - Case, circa 1842 (Box 6, Folder 40)
        Brown leatherette flip-top case for a sixth plate cased photograph with a light tan pad
        Inscription on lining paper: "Wm. Sage, Berlin, Ct, manufacturer of miniature cases" and "17"
        Accompanied by a gilt paper mat with an inscription on its verso, "17"
    - Smith
      - Case, circa 1840-1842 (Box 6, Folder 41)
        Red leatherette oval case for a sixth plate cased photograph or miniature painting with a white pad
        Affixed label on lining cloth: "Made at Smith's, No. 2, Milk St., opposite Old South, Boston"
    - Unidentified Manufacturers
      - Case, circa 1845-1850; (2 cases) (Box 6, Folder 42-43)
        Leatherette flip-top plain cases with corner designs for a ninth plate cased photographs with green velvet pads
      - Case, circa 1845-1850 (Box 6, Folder 44)
        Leatherette flip-top plain case for a ninth plate cased photograph with red velvet pad
        Includes brass oval mat and cover glass
      - Case, circa 1845-1850 (Box 6, Folder 45)
      - Half case, circa 1845-1850 (Box 6, Folder 46)
        Half case for a ninth plate cased photograph with red velvet pad with a floral vase
- Stereographs, 1850-1975; Series II; 4.2; 5 boxes
  Series II is organized into seven subseries: Daguerreotype Stereographs, Ambrotypes Stereographs, Tintype Stereographs, Glass Stereographs, Salted Paper Print Stereographs, Stereographs, Tissue Stereographs, and Card Stereographs.
  Headings in each subseries are arranged alphabetically by identified creators followed by items with unidentified creators. Items under each name are arranged either chronologically, alphabetically by title, or sequentially by stereograph number.
  This series consists of stereoscopic photographs in different formats, including daguerreotypes, ambrotypes, tintypes, glass, salted paper print, and tissue stereographs, as well as general stereograph cards that possess albumen and silver gelatin photographic prints.
  Stereographs are double photographic prints that depict the same image taken from two slightly different perspectives and mounted on cards. Viewing the two-dimensional images through a stereoscope creates the illusion of a three-dimensional image to the viewer.
  Entries for stereographs in each subseries include their titles, numbers on the mounts, and their series. The entries also document if no numbers or series information exists.
  Entries may occasionally include descriptions of the images to clarify the subjects of the stereographs.
  - Daguerreotype Stereographs
    - Claudet, Antoine François Jean
      Antoine François Jean Claudet (1797-1867) was a French photographer active in Great Britain. From 1851-1867 he operated a studio at 107 Regent Street in London.
      - Daguerreotype stereograph, not in a case, a studio genre scene depicting two women seated and a woman standing, as well as a parrot, circa 1855 (Box 7, Folder 47)
        Label affixed to verso of plate: By special appointment to her Majesty, Mr. Antoine Claudet, 107 Regent Street. (Quadrant near Vico Street)
    - Unidentified photographer
      - Daguerreotype stereograph, in a case, a studio portrait of an elderly woman, circa 1855-1860 (Box 7, Folder 48)
        Leather case with collapsible stereoscopic lenses and gilt imprint: "Mascher's Improved Stereoscope, Philada. Patent March 8th 1853"
        Pencil inscription on case under the image package: "Jedidiah Hall"
  - Ambrotype Stereographs
    - Douglas, John
      John Douglas was a portrait painter and photographer in Glasgow, Scotland, 1857-1886.
      - Ambrotype stereograph, not in a case, a studio portrait of a woman seated and a man standing, 1857-1865 (Box 7, Folder 49)
        Hand-tinted ambrotype stereograph with a black painted mount
        Label affixed to verso of plate: "From John Douglas, portrait painter and photographer, 145 Sauchiehall Street, Glasgow"
    - Simonton and Millard
      Simonton and Millard was the photographic partnership of James Simonton and Thomas Millard in Dublin, Ireland, 1858-1862
      - Ambrotype stereograph, not in a case, a studio portrait of a girl and three boys, 1858-1862 (Box 7, Folder 50)
        Hand-tinted ambrotype stereograph with a black and gilt-painted mount
        Label affixed to verso of plate: "Photographed by Simonton and Millard, Dublin Photographic Institution, 39, Lower Sackville-Street, near the general post office"
    - Unidentified photographers
      - Ambrotype stereograph, not in a case, a view of the sculpture, Eurydice mourante, by Charles-François Lebœuf (1792-1865), also known as Nanteuil, in the Crystal Palace of the Great Exhibition of the Works of Industry of all Nations, 1851 (Box 7, Folder 51)
      - Ambrotype stereograph of a studio portrait of a woman seated, circa 1855-1865 (Box 7, Folder 52)